In the previous video, we introduced the concept
of price-per-click and click-through-rate.
Once we know both of these quantities,
we can calculate the average price per display.
This is simply the average amount
that an advertiser pays when a user is shown their ad.
We can compute this by multiplying the price-per-click
with the click-through-rate.
Let's go through an example to see how this works.
Suppose we have 10 users who search for "best LTE network".
Google decides to display Verizon's ad to all of them.
We know that the click-through-rate for Verizon
and for the "best LTE network" query is 0.2, so only two users
click on the ad.
Verizon must now pay the price-per-click
for each of these users.
Since there were two clicks and each click costs $25,
Verizon must pay a total of $50 to Google.
If we consider how much Verizon paid to Google on average,
per user, or equivalently how much Verizon paid per display
of the ad, we just divide the total amount
of $50 for the 10 users who saw the ad.
Doing this, we see that the average price per display
was $5.
We could have obtained this amount in a simpler way.
In particular, as we defined in the previous slide,
this turns out to be exactly the same as the price-per-click
multiplied by the click-through-rate.
For our data then, to obtain the average price per display
we simply need to multiply the price-per-click table
and the click-through-rate tables together.
The last piece of data that we need
before we can define our problem is
we need to know how popular the queries are.
Obviously, Google does not control how many times
a search query will be searched because the users are
the ones who submit the queries.
However, Google does have an estimate
of the number of times, on average,
the query will be requested over a given day.
For the example that we have been building so far,
let's suppose that we expect to see "4G LTE" 140 times,
"largest LTE" 80 times, and "best LTE network" 80 times,
as well.
We're now ready to start modeling this problem.
The problem that we will consider is this.
How many times should Google display each ad for each query,
so as to maximize their total revenue?
In the next video, we will formulate
this as a linear optimization problem.