The overall revenue management problem
involves a network of airports and literally thousands
of flights.
Clearly optimization is needed.
Myopic solutions leave significant revenue
on the table.
Furthermore, revenue management involves
tens of different classes that have different restrictions,
different characteristics like mile awards, and fares.
PEOPLExpress could not compete with American Airlines'
Ultimate Super Saver fares.
Donald Burr, CEO of PEOPLExpress in 1985,
notes, "We were a vibrant, profitable company
from 1981 to 1985, and then we tipped right over
into losing $50 million a month.
We had been profitable from the day
we started until American came at us with Ultimate Super
Savers."
Revenue management is the science
of selling the right seats to the right customers
at the right prices.
To illustrate the impact that revenue management has
had on American Airlines, we note
what Robert Crandall, CEO of American,
wrote during the period that revenue management
practices were applied.
"Revenue management is the single most important
technical development in transportation management
since we entered the era of airline deregulation.
We estimate that revenue management
has generated $1.4 billion in incremental revenue
in the last three years."
Let us see the impact of revenue management more broadly.
Today, American Airlines has emerged from bankruptcy
by merging with US Air Airlines.
However, American Airlines has spun
off Sabre Holdings, the entity that
built revenue management for American.
As of November 2012, Sabre ranked 133rd
among America's largest private companies with $3.15 billion
in sales, 400 airlines, 90,000 hotels, and 30 car rental
companies as clients.
Today, companies prosper from revenue management.
Delta Airlines, for example, increased annual revenue
by $300 million.
Marriott hotels increased annual revenue by $100 million.