Let's look at how sports scheduling can
be done with optimization by starting with a small example.
Suppose we're trying to schedule a tournament between four
teams-- Atlanta, Boston, Chicago, and Detroit.
We'll call these teams A, B, C, and D.
These teams are divided into two divisions.
Atlanta and Boston are in one division,
and Chicago and Detroit are in the second division.
Each team plays one game a week for a total of four weeks.
During the four weeks, each team plays the other team
in the same division twice, and each team
plays the teams in the other divisions once.
The team with the most wins from each division
will play in the championship game.
For this reason, teams prefer to play divisional games later.
If team A plays team C and D in the first two weeks
and wins both games while team B also plays team C and D
and loses both games, A knows that they only
need to win one of the games against B
to beat B in terms of wins and to go to the championship.
We can schedule this tournament by using an optimization model.
Our objective is to maximize team preferences, which
are that teams would like to play divisional games later.
Our decisions are which teams should
play each other each week.
And we have three types of constraints.
Each team needs to play the other team in their division
twice, each team needs to play the teams in the other division
once, and each team should play exactly one team each week.
Let's start by discussing our decision variables.
We need to decide which teams will play each other each week.
To do this, let's define decision variables
which we'll call x_ijk.
If team i plays team j in week k,
then x_ijk will be equal to 1.
Otherwise, x_ijk equals 0.
As an example, suppose team A plays team C in week 2.
Then x_AC2 would equal 1.
Since A only plays C once, we should have then
that x_AC1, or A playing C in week 1, should be equal to 0.
Similarly, x_AC3 should equal 0, and x_AC4 should equal 0.
This is called a binary decision variable
since it's a decision variable that
can only take two values, 0 and 1.
This is a new type of decision variable,
and it's what makes integer optimization
different from linear optimization.
The decision variables in integer optimization
can only take integer values.
This includes binary decision variables,
like the ones we have here, that can only be either 0 or 1.
These variables can model decisions
like where to build a new warehouse,
whether or not to invest in a stock,
or assigning nurses to shifts.
Integer optimization problems can also
have integer decision variables that take values 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
etc.
These variables can model decisions
like the number of new machines to purchase,
the number of workers to assign for a shift,
and the number of items to stock in a store.
Other than the new types of variables, integer optimization
is exactly like linear optimization.
But we'll see this week how integer optimization variables,
and especially binary variables, can increase our modeling
capabilities.
Now let's go back to our formulation.
As we said before, our decisions are
which teams should play each other each week.
We'll model this with the binary decision variables
we just discussed-- x_ijk which equal 1
if team i plays team j in week k.
Now let's use these decision variables
to form our constraints.
The first constraint is that each team
should play the other team in their division twice.
So teams A and B should play each other twice
in the four weeks.
This can be modeled with the constraint x_AB1 + x_AB2 +
x_AB3 + x_AB4 = 2.
This will force two of these decision variables
to be equal to 1, and the other two decision variables
to be equal to 0.
The ones that are equal to 1 will correspond to the weeks
that A and B will play each other.
We'll have a similar constraint for teams C and D.
Our next constraint is that each team
should play the teams in the other division once.
So teams A and C should play each other once
in the four weeks.
This can be modeled with a constraint x_AC1 + x_AC2 +
x_AC3 + x_AC4 = 1.
This is very similar to the previous constraint,
except this time only one of the decision variables
will have value 1.
We'll have similar constraints for teams A and D,
teams B and C, and teams B and D. Our last type of constraint
is that each team should play exactly one
other team each week.
This means that A should play B, C or D in week 1.
This can be modeled with a constraint x_AB1
+ x_AC1 + x_AD1 = 1.
Exactly one of these decision variables will be equal to 1,
meaning that A will play that team in week 1.
We'll have a similar constraint for every team and week pair.
Now, let's model our objective.
Let's assume that teams have a preference of 1
for playing divisional games in week 1, a preference of 2
for playing divisional games in week 2, a preference of 4
for playing divisional games in week 3, and a preference of 8
for playing divisional games in week 4.
So the preference doubles with each later week.
Then we can model our objective as x_AB1 + 2*x_AB2 + 4*x_AB3 +
8*x_AB4 + x_CD1 + 2*x_CD2 + 4*x_CD3 + 8*x_CD4.
Then if team AB plays in week 3, we'll add 4 to our objective.
If they play in week 1, then we'll
only add 1 to our objective.
If they don't play in a week, that term will be 0
and will not contribute to the objective.
Now that we've set up our problem,
we're ready to solve it.
In the next video, we'll set up and solve our problem
in LibreOffice.